The red, headed league one day last autumn
i went to see my friend sherlock holmes.
He was talking to a fat old man with red
hair. I wanted to go away. But holmes
pulled me into the room and closed the
door.
You came at a good time, watson, holmes
said. I thought you were busy. I am busy.
But stay. This is mr. Wilson. He helped me
in many cases. He will help us today too.
Mr. Wilson stood up a little and said
hello. Sit on the sofa,
Holmes said. He sat in his chair and put
his fingers together. Watson, you like
strange stories. You wrote about my work.
Thank you. Holmes said to wilson, please
tell your story again. Watson did not hear
the start.
I need all the details. Wilson took an old
newspaper from his coat. He looked at the
advertisements. I looked at wilson. He was
a normal shop man. He was fat and slow. He
wore grey trousers and a black coat.
Nothing was special except his very red
hair and his unhappy face. Holmes smiled
at me. He said, this man worked with his
hands. He uses snuff. He is a freemason.
He was in china. He writes a lot. Wilson
jumped up. Mr. Holmes!
How do you know that? Your right hand is
bigger than your left hand. You worked
with it. That is true. I was a ship
carpenter. And the snuff? And the
freemason pin on your shirt? Wilson
laughed loudly.
At first i thought you were very clever.
But now i see it is not magic. Holmes said
to me, watson, i should not explain
everything. Mr. Wilson, can you find the
advertisement? Yes. Here it is. This is
where it all started.
Please read it, sir.
I took the paper and read it. To the red,
headed league a rich american man left
money for men with red hair. There is a
new job. You can get four pounds every
week for easy work. Red, headed men over21
years can apply.
Come on monday at eleven o'clock to duncan
ross, seven pope's court, fleet street.
What does this mean? I asked. Holmes
laughed. It is strange, isn't it? Now, mr.
Wilson, tell us about yourself and this
advertisement.
Holmes said to me, watson, write down the
paper and the date. It is the morning
chronicle,27 april1890. Wilson wiped his
face. Mr. Holmes, i have a small pawn shop
in coburg square. The shop is not big.
I can live, but i do not earn much money.
I have one assistant now. His name is
vincent spaulding. He works for half pay
because he wants to learn the business. He
is smart. He can find a better job, but he
stays with me.
Does he take photos? Holmes asked. Yes.
That is his problem. He takes photos and
goes to the cellar. But he is a good
worker. Do you live alone? No. Spaulding
lives with me. A girl of fourteen cooks
and cleans.
I have no wife and no children. We live
quietly. Eight weeks ago spaulding came to
me with this paper. He said, mr. Wilson, i
wish i had red hair. There is a new job in
the red, headed league. It pays good
money. I stay at home a lot,
Wilson said. I did not know about this
league. Never heard of it? That is
surprising. You can apply. The pay is
about two hundred pounds a year. The work
is easy. Wilson's ears went up. His
business was not good. Extra money would
help.
Spaulding explained. A rich american,
ezekiah hopkins, loved men with red hair.
When he died, trustees used his money to
help red, headed men in london. The hair
must be bright red, not light red or dark
red. Wilson looked at his hair.
It was bright red. Spaulding knew a lot
about the league. Wilson closed the shop
for the day.
Spaulding said, come with me now. He was
happy to have a holiday. We closed the
shop and went to the address in the
advertisement. Mr. Holmes, i never saw so
many red, headed men. They came from the
north, south, east, and west.
Fleet street was full of them. Pope's
court looked like a market of red hair.
There was yellow hair, orange hair, brown
hair, but not many men had bright red hair
like mine. I wanted to go home. There were
too many people.
But spaulding would not listen. He pushed
me through the crowd to the office steps.
Many men went up the stairs with hope.
Many came down with sad faces. We went up
too. Holmes said, please continue. The
office was very small.
There were only two wooden chairs and a
table. Behind the table sat a small man.
His hair was even redder than mine. He
spoke to each man for a short time. He
always found a small problem and said no.
So the job was not easy to get.
When it was our turn, the man was much
nicer to me than to the others. He closed
the door. This is mr. Jabez wilson,
spaulding said. He wants the job in the
league. You are perfect for it, the man
said.
He looked at my hair for a long time. I
felt shy. Then he pulled my hair with both
hands to see if it was real. It hurt and
my eyes watered. He said they were careful
because some men used wigs or paint.
Then he opened the window and shouted that
the job was full. The other men went away
in different directions. My name is duncan
ross, he said. I also get money from the
league fund. Are you married? Do you have
children? No, i said.
He looked very serious. The money was also
to help families with red hair. I thought
i would not get the job. But after a few
minutes he said it was all right for me
because my hair was so bright. I already
have a pawn shop, i said.
Do not worry, spaulding said. I can watch
your shop. What are the hours? I asked.
From ten in the morning to two in the
afternoon, ross said. That was good for
me.
My shop is busy in the evening, especially
on thursday and friday before payday. You
must stay in the office, or at least in
the building, all the time, ross said. If
you go out, you lose the job forever. What
is the work? I asked.
You must copy the encyclopaedia
britannica, he said. Here is the first
book. We give the table and chair. You
bring ink, pens, and paper. Can i start
tomorrow? Yes, i said. He said goodbye and
congratulated me again.
I went home with spaulding. I was very
happy. But in the evening i thought again.
Maybe it was a trick. Maybe nobody pays
good money only to copy a book. Spaulding
tried to make me feel better. I almost did
not go the next day.
The next day i took ink and paper and went
to pope's court. Everything was ready. Mr.
Ross started me on the letter a and
sometimes came to check me. At two o'clock
he locked the door and paid me on
saturday, four gold coins every week.
This went on for eight weeks. I wrote
about abbots, archery, armor, and many
words under a. I did not leave the room
because i did not want to lose the job.
Then this morning the door was locked. A
small card was on the door.
It said, the red, headed league is
dissolved.9 october1890. Holmes and i
looked at the card. We laughed. Wilson was
angry. This is not funny! No, no, holmes
said. Please sit down. This case is very
interesting. What did you do?
I did not know what to do. I asked in the
offices nearby. Nobody knew the league. I
asked the landlord downstairs. He never
heard of the red, headed league. I asked
about duncan ross. He said the red, haired
man was william morris, a lawyer.
He moved out yesterday. He said the new
address was17 king edward street. I went
there. It was a factory for artificial
knees. Nobody knew morris or ross. What
did you do then? Holmes asked. I went
home.
Spaulding said to wait for a letter. That
was not enough. I heard you help people,
so i came to you. You did the right thing,
holmes said. Maybe this is more serious
than it looks. I lost four pounds a week!
Wilson said.
But you earned thirty pounds and learned
many words under a, holmes said. You did
not lose money. You want to know who they
are and why they did this. Yes. It cost
them thirty, two pounds. We will find
answers.
How long has spaulding worked for you?
About one month. He answered an
advertisement. Twelve men applied.
Why did you choose him? He was useful and
cheap. Half wages. What does he look like?
He is small and strong. He moves fast. He
has no beard. He is about thirty. He has a
white mark from acid on his forehead.
Holmes sat up fast.
I thought so. Are his ears pierced for
earrings? Yes. He said a gypsy did it when
he was a boy. Holmes thought deeply. Is he
still at the shop? Yes. I left him there
this morning. The shop was fine. Thank
you, mr. Wilson.
I will tell you my answer in a day or two.
When wilson left, holmes asked me, what do
you think, watson? I do not understand it.
Strange stories are often simple. I need
to think. Do not talk to me for fifty
minutes.
Holmes smoked and closed his eyes. Then he
jumped up. Sarasate plays at st. James's
hall today. Come with me, watson. We took
the underground to aldersgate and walked
to saxe, coburg square. It was a small,
poor, quiet square.
Wilson's pawn shop had three gold balls
outside, the sign of a pawn shop. Holmes
looked at the shop and walked up and down
the street. Then he knocked on the door. A
young clean, shaven man opened it.
Holmes asked, how do i go to the strand?
Third right, fourth left, the man said
quickly, and closed the door. A smart man!
Holmes said. Maybe the fourth smartest man
in london. You wanted to see the
assistant, not the way, i said.
No. I wanted to see his trousers knees.
Why did you hit the pavement with your
stick? Now we observe, watson. We are like
spies. We walked around the corner to a
big busy street with many shops.
Holmes named the buildings, a tobacconist,
a bank, a restaurant, a carriage shop.
Now, doctor, work is finished. Let us eat
and go to the concert. In the afternoon
holmes listened to music and was very
happy. His face looked dreamy, not like
the sharp detective i knew.
But i felt danger was coming for the
criminals he hunted. When we left, holmes
said, go home, watson. I have work. This
case is serious. A crime is planned. We
can stop it. I need you tonight at ten.
Bring your gun. He left in the crowd.
I did not understand what he knew. I
thought about the red, headed league, the
shop, and the bank. At a quarter past nine
i came to baker street. Two cabs waited
outside. Holmes talked with two men, peter
jones from scotland yard, and mr.
Merryweather from the bank, a thin sad man
in a black coat. Our group is ready,
holmes said. Watson, this is jones. This
is merryweather. Tonight's game is bigger
than cards. For you, mr.
Merryweather, thirty thousand pounds are
at risk, holmes said. For you, jones, the
man is john clay, a thief and forger, one
of the best criminals in london. I hope we
do not chase a wild goose, merryweather
said. Trust holmes,
Jones said. It is after ten. Let us go,
holmes said. Holmes was quiet in the cab.
We drove through london to farringdon
street. We are near, holmes said.
Merryweather is a bank director. Jones is
brave and will not let go.
We walked through a narrow passage and
down stone steps behind iron doors.
Merryweather lit a lantern. We entered a
large dark cellar full of boxes. Holmes
looked around. Not easy to attack from
above.
Merryweather hit the floor with his stick.
The floor sounded hollow. Please be quiet,
holmes said. You can break our plan. Sit
on those boxes. Holmes knelt and looked at
the floor with a magnifying glass. Then he
stood up.
We have about one hour, he said. We are in
the cellar of a big london bank. The bank
keeps french gold here, thirty thousand
gold coins. Criminals want this gold. We
must turn off the light and wait, holmes
said.
Hide behind the boxes. When i shine my
light, run fast. Watson, if they shoot,
you can shoot too. I put my gun ready.
Holmes turned off the lantern. It was
completely dark and cold. We waited in
silence.
Holmes whispered, they can only go back to
wilson's shop. Jones, are men at the front
door? Yes. An inspector and two policemen.
Good. Now we wait. It felt like all night,
but it was only about one hour.
I was tired and afraid to move. I heard my
friends breathing. Then i saw a small
light on the floor. It became a yellow
line. A hand came up through the stones
and moved in the light. Then the hand went
away. Everything was dark again.
For a minute a hand came up through the
floor, then went back. A stone moved. A
hole opened. Light came up. A young man
climbed out. A small man with red hair
followed. It's clear, he whispered. Do you
have the bags?
Holmes caught the first man. The second
man tried to escape down the hole. Jones
caught his coat. A gun fell when holmes
hit the man's arm. It's no use, john clay,
holmes said. Clay smiled. You did well.
Your red, headed league trick was clever.
Police took clay away. Merryweather
thanked holmes for saving the bank gold.
Later at baker street holmes told me
again, the league was only a trick to keep
wilson away.
Clay dug from the cellar to the bank. When
the office closed, the tunnel was ready.
They chose saturday night to steal and
escape on sunday. You see every step, i
said. Yes, holmes said.
Now i need a little rest, and maybe
another strange case soon.